Register of the Lester Ziffren Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lester Ziffren Papers
1933-1989
90009
Ziffren, Lester
8 manuscript boxes (3.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Lester Ziffren papers contain materials relating to the Spanish Civil War. As Madrid bureau chief for United Press, Ziffren filed dispatches and made nightly radio broadcasts in which he described political, economic, and social conditions in Spain in the period prior to the outbreak of the Civil War and during the first six months of the conflict itself. The Speeches and Writings series of the papers contains compilations of Ziffren's articles and dispatches, as well as transcripts of his radio broadcasts. There are also two sets of diary entries in the series, including his diary from the opening months of the Civil War, and several later articles in which Ziffren recounts his experiences as a war correspondent.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1906 Born, Rock Island, Illinois
1927 Graduated from the University of Missouri's journalism school
1933-1936 Bureau chief for United Press in Madrid, Spain
1937-1940 Worked as a screenwriter in Hollywood
1941-1945 Public relations officer, U.S. Embassy in Santiago, Chile
1961-1971 Public relations director, Kennecott Copper Corporation
2007 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Lester Ziffren papers contain significant materials relating to the Spanish Civil War. As Madrid bureau chief for United Press, Ziffren filed dispatches and made nightly radio broadcasts in which he described political, economic, and social conditions in Spain in the period prior to the outbreak of the Civil War and during the first six months of the conflict itself. The Speeches and writings contains compilations of Ziffren's articles and dispatches, as well as transcripts of his radio broadcasts. There are also two sets of diary entries in the series, including his diary from the opening months of the Civil War, and several later articles in which Ziffren recounts his experiences as a war correspondent.
The Biographical file series contains clippings and an interview with Ziffren about his time in Spain. The Writings by others contains articles on the Spanish Civil War written by other correspondents and a diary kept by Tomás Caro, a volunteer in the Republican army. The Printed matter series of the papers is comprised of materials largely relating to the Civil War. It includes numerous clippings from Spanish, English and American newspapers, as well as bulletins and serial issues pertaining to the conflict. Additionally, there are some monographs and other printed matter relating to Spain in the Franco era. The Photographs contains prints depicting scenes of the Civil War, as well as prints that depict cities, towns, and rural life in Spain.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 6 series: Biographical file; Cables sent to United Press; Speeches and writings; Writings by others on the Spanish Civil War; Printed matter relating to Spain and the Spanish Civil War; Photographs
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain--Politics and government--1931-1939.; Spain--Social conditions--1886-1939.; Journalists.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1935-1982 (Box 1)
  Contains clippings and a transcript of a radio interview, arranged by physical form
  - Clippings, 1935-1982 (Folder 1)
    - 1935-1937 (Folder 1: 1)
    - 1937 (Folder 1: 2)
    - 1982 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Transcript of radio interview conducted by Lowell Thomas, 1937 (Folder 1: 4)
- Cables sent to United Press, 1936 (Box 1: 5)
  Consists of one folder of cablegrams
- Speeches and writings, 1933-1937 (Box 1-5)
  Contains articles; compilations of articles, dispatches, and transcribed radio broadcasts; and diaries, arranged by title or form
  - Diary, 1933-1934 (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Spain Day by Day," a compilation of transcribed United Press radio broadcasts and dispatches, 1933-1936 (Folder 1-4)
    - 1933 September-October (Folder 1: 7)
    - 1934 (Folder 1-2)
      - January-June (Folder 1: 8)
      - July-December (Folder 2: 1)
    - 1935 (Folder 2-3)
      - January-June (Folder 2: 2)
      - July-December (Folder 3: 1)
    - 1936 January-June (Folder 4: 1)
  - "Spanish Letters," a compilation of United Press articles and dispatches, 1933-1936 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Articles written for United Press, 1936-1937 (Folder 5: 2)
  - "Diary of a Civil War Correspondent,", 1936-1937 (Folder 5: 3)
  - "Spain in Upheaval," Current History, 1936 May (Folder 5: 4)
  - "I Lived in Madrid," Current History, 1937 April (Folder 5: 5)
  - "The Correspondent in Spain," The Public Opinion Quarterly, 1937 July (Folder 5: 6)
- Writings by others on the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1940 (Box 5)
  Contains articles and a diary, arranged alphabetically by author
  - Allen, Jay, 1937 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Carro, Tomás, 1940 (Folder 5: 8)
    Includes correspondence
  - Fernsworth, Lawrence A., 1936 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Fischer, Louis, 1936-1937 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Newbigging, Duncan, 1936 (Folder 5: 11)
- Printed matter relating to Spain and the Spanish Civil War, 1934-1989 (Box 6-8)
  Contains bulletins, clippings, map, monographs, pamphlets, postcards, and serial issues, arranged by physical form
  - Bulletins, 1936-1980 (Folder 6)
    - 1936 (Folder 6: 1)
    - 1937 (Folder 6: 2-3)
    - 1946 (Folder 6: 4)
    - 1950 (Folder 6: 5)
    - 1980 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Clippings, 1934-1986 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1934 (Folder 6: 7)
    - 1935 (Folder 6: 8)
    - 1936 (Folder 6: 9-12)
    - 1937 (Folder 6: 13-17)
    - 1938 (Folder 6: 18-19)
    - 1939 (Folder 7: 1-3)
    - 1940 (Folder 7: 4-5)
    - 1946-1950 (Folder 7: 6)
    - 1966-1986 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Map, 1936 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Monographs, 1937-1966 (Folder 7)
    - 1937 (Folder 7: 9)
    - 1940 (Folder 7: 10-14)
    - 1946 (Folder 7: 15)
    - 1949 (Folder 7: 16)
    - 1966 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Pamphlets, 1936-1989 (Folder 8)
    - 1936 (Folder 8: 1-2)
    - 1937 (Folder 8: 3-4)
    - 1938-1939 (Folder 8: 5)
    - 1940 (Folder 8: 6-7)
    - 1974-1989 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Postcards, 1936 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Serial issues, 1936-1989 (Folder 8)
    - 1936 (Folder 8: 10-11)
    - 1938 (Folder 8: 12)
    - 1961 (Folder 8: 13)
    - 1989 (Folder 8: 14)
- Photographs, 1936 (Box 8:)
  Consists of prints depicting scenes of the Spanish Civil War and of Spain, arranged by subject
  - Thirty-one prints depicting scenes of the Spanish Civil War, 1936 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Twenty-one prints depicting various cities, towns, and rural life in Spain, 1936 (Folder 8: 15)